James Reese collection, 1941-1983, bulk 1954-1983
George Eastman Museum
James Reese collection,bulk
1941-1983,
1954-1983
1.5 cubic feet
George Eastman Museum
George Eastman Museum Moving Image Department 900 East Avenue Rochester, NY 14607 Phone: 585-271-3361 Fax: 585-256-3397 Email: stills@eastman.org URL: www.eastman.org
The James Reese collection consists of artwork, awards, scripts, and materials from film labs, all of which are related to Reese's work. It also consists of 16mm prints of his films, as well as films he collected.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to research upon request.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by the estate of James Reese in 1994, 1998, and 2005.
Collection materials were created or collected by Mr. Reese and maintained by him during his lifetime.
Funding for this finding aid was provided by a grant from the Council on Library and Information Resources’ Hidden Collections Program.
Biographical Note
James Harold Reese (often credited as “Jay Reese”) was born on May 20, 1914. His early career in film production was dedicated to industrial films, but towards the end of his life he explored his interest in ethnographic, sociological, and nature films.
Reese attended the University of Washington, where he was a member of the Kappa Sigma fraternity and the university basketball team. He received a Bachelor of Arts in August 1938 and a Master of Arts in English in August 1939 with a thesis titled "Emerson and Spinoza: a Comparative Study of Their Metaphysics and Ethics and Emerson's Position as a Monistic Thinker.”
In the 1950s and early 1960s, Reese served as Production Supervisor of the Motion Picture Unit of General Electric's Heavy Military Electronics Department in Syracuse, New York. While at General Electric Reese was involved in a number of industrial film productions, including the Golden Eagle award-winning Hands of Industry( 1962 ).
Reese was employed by the College at Brockport, State University of New York (SUNY Brockport) from 1966 to 1974. When he left, he was listed in staff directories as Assistant Director of Cinematography, ECC (Educational Communication Center). During his time there he was involved in the production of numerous films about the university and the local environment, as well as more personal interests. These films include a series on the Bergen Swamp shot over the course of several seasons, an orientation film for SUNY Brockport entitled What is a College?( ca. 1968 ), and the Golden Eagle award-winning,The Faces of Jocotepec( 1970 ) about the disappearing native cultures of Mexico.
James Reese passed away on October 11, 1993.
Scope and Content Note
The James Reese collection consists of scripts, photographs, films, illustrations by Reese, awards, and materials from film laboratories. The materials are predominantly professional rather than personal. They do not cover the entirety of his career; most of the materials are from Reese's time at SUNY Brockport, and there are some materials dating from his time with General Electric. Geographically, the collection covers work done in the United States and Mexico.
A particular strength of the collection is material related to film production, with numerous timing cards and information from film-processing labs.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into five series, based on topic or medium: Art/Photographs, Awards, Film Lab/Production Materials, Films, and Scripts. The films are stored separately from the other materials, which are housed in one standard-sized archival box and one medium-sized flat box. Prior to processing, all materials that were not films were stored in a single standard-sized archival box. This rehousing was done for reasons of size and safekeeping. The details of the five series that comprise the collection are as follows:
Series 1, Art/Photographs, 1956-1983
Series 2, Awards, 1960-1970
Series 3, Film Lab/Production Materials, 1969-1975 ,undated
Series 4, Films, 1941-1973, undated
Series 5, Scripts, 1954-ca. 1973, undated
Bobear, Jean B., 1922-2009; Reese, James, 1914-1993
Byron Motion Pictures; General Electric Corporation; State University of New York College at Brockport
Botany -- New York (State); Ethnographic films -- United States; Education, Higher -- New York (State); Industrial films; Indian art -- Northwest Coast of North America; Indians of Mexico
acetate film; albums (books); awards; black-and-white photographs; booklets; brochures; business records; clippings (information artifacts); color photographs; commercial correspondence; drawings (visual works); filmmaking and filmmaking processes and techniques; grant proposals; notes; photograph albums; programs (documents); screenplays; shipping records; trophies (objects)
Related Collections
The Rose Archives at the College of Brockport
The College of Brockport, State University of New York Drake Memorial Library https://www.brockport.edu/about/archives/
SUNY Brockport also houses collections related to the history of western New York State which may be relevant to the study of James Reese. Please contact the college archivist for further details.
Container List
- Series 1, Art/Photographs, 1956-1983
  Scope and Content
  Series consists of photographs and drawings. Photographs show Reese throughout his career and subjects from film projects. Illustrations are for his film The Theft of the Sun( 1957 ).
  Arrangement
  Series consists of four albums, all housed in Box C111. Original order was maintained.
  - no title (Box C111)
    - The Faces of Jocotepec– Falisco, Mexico, 1972-1980 (Folder 21)
      Photo album, with black and white photos affixed to pages in a spiral-bound red book, alongside an extensive write-up on the film.
    - “Plants, Art, & Architecture In the Americas – The Maya, Mixtec, & Zapotec of Mexico” – James H. Reese, Brockport, New York, 1983 (Folder 22)
      Photo album, in the form of a spiral-bound green book. Color photographs are placed alongside an extensive write-up and captions.
    - [Unlabeled Blue Album],,, and, 1956; 1962; 1970-1971 (Folder 29)
      Contains photographs and clippings, mostly of Reese, and a brief biography of Reese from a convention flyer. Includes reproduction of a childhood photo of Reese, from ca. 1923.
    - [Unlabeled Black Album], 1957 (Folder 31)
      Bound album, with black and white illustrations, photographs, and a typed script for The Theft of the Sun.
- Series 2, Awards, 1960-1970
  Series consists of one three-dimensional object and one folder containing certificates and awards for Reese’s work for General Electric and the work he did while at SUNY Brockport.
  Items are housed in a box designated for oversized materials. They were originally in box C111.
  - no title (Box C111-OS)
    - James H. Reese Film Awards,,, and, 1961-1963; 1967; 1970 (Folder 3)
      Folder contains certificates and awards for the following films:The Prosperity of Water,The Hands of Industry,Dr. Lipschitz’s Fairytale,The Faces of Jocotepec, and Audio-Visual Tutorial Program in Principles of Biology
    - Annual Industrial Film Award, 1960 (Folder 4)
      Certificate of Merit awarded to the General Electric Company for The Prosperity of Water in the class of public relations, September 1960. Item is a certificate laminated on wood suitable for hanging. Size is approximately 15" x 12".
- Series 3, Film Lab/Production Materials,, undated, 1969-1975
  Series consists of 18 folders containing price lists, promotional materials, shipping memos, and timing cards from film labs related to the production of Reese’s films. This series also contains notes and labels that were found inside film cans in this collection.
  All folders are housed in Box C111 Box C111-OS. Many folders consist of items originally found in film cans.
  - no title (Box C111)
    - ["Botany" Project Materials], 1969; 1971 (Folder 5)
      Material related to "Botany" project. Information about this footage, research and development grant proposal, sequence of scenes, and correspondence.
    - Active Contract Price Lists, 1969; 1972 (Folder 6)
      Film laboratory price lists; Consolidated Film Industries motion picture film calculator.
    - [The Faces of Jocotepec- Notes and Labels], ca. 1970 (Folder 7)
      Notes and labels found inside The Faces of Jocotepec film cans.
    - [History,The Mayas, and Palenque- Timing Cards], 1972-1973 (Folder 8)
      Film printer timing card for "History,The Mayas Prod. #149," dated 1972 and film printer timing card for "Prod. #160 Palenque." Both are from Byron Motion Pictures.
    - [Bergen Swamp- Fall 1970- Timing Card] (Folder 9)
      Byron Motion Pictures timing card for Bergen Swamp - Fall 1970.
    - ["Botany" - Timing Card], 1970 (Folder 10)
      Byron Motion Pictures timing card for Prod. #122 "Botany" and notes on index card.
    - ["Botany" - Shipping Memo], 1970 (Folder 11)
      Byron Motion Pictures shipping memo and timing card for Prod. #122 "Botany."
    - [Dance #1 Chaconne in D Minor- Timing Card], 1971 (Folder 12)
      Byron Motion Pictures timing card for Dance #1 Chaconne in D Minor."
    - [Bergen Swamp - July 1970- Timing Card], 1973 (Folder 13)
      Byron Motion Pictures timing card for Bergen Swamp - July 1970.
    - [Bergen Swamp - Spring 1969 and Bergen Swamp- Lab Order and Shipping Memo], 1969-1970 (Folder 14)
      Capital Film Laboratories daily lab order for Bergen Swamp - Spring 1969; Byron Motion Pictures shipping memo for Bergen Swamp; notes
    - [Bergen Swamp- Label], undated (Folder 15)
      Label from film can for Bergen Swamp- "Violets and Periwinkle Original."
    - [The Faces of Jocotepec- Mixing Cue Sheets], ca. 1970 (Folder 16)
      Byron Motion Pictures mixing cue sheets for reels 1 and 2 of The Faces of Jocotepec.
    - [The Faces of Jocotepec- Labels and Notes], undated (Folder 17)
      Labels and notes from film can.
    - [Dance #3 Field of Light- Timing Card], 1971 (Folder 18)
      Byron Motion Pictures timing card for Dance #3 Field of Light.
    - [The Faces of Jocotepec- Labels], ca. 1970 (Folder 19)
      Labels from The Faces of Jocotepec film can.
    - [Unlabeled box of index cards], undated (Folder 32)
      Index cards organized alphabetically by name of shot and roll number, with list of camera shots.
  - no title (Box C111-OS)
    - Kirby and Maya Titles, 1973 (Folder 1)
      Title cards for "Reese – Palenque – 1973," "Trees in Flower," "Cities of the Ancient Mayas," and a Part 1 title card for "Palenque 300-900 A.D.," as well as some production cards.
    - Byron Color-Correct Film List, 1975 (Folder 2)
      Promotional folder from Byron Film and Video Laboratories, includes price list and note from the company.
- Series 4, Films,, undated, 1941-1973
  Series consists of approximately 45 individual titles. All material is housed in 16mm single and double reel cans and consists of prints, reversal material, A/B rolls, sound track, ¼” tape, trims, and out-takes. Titles may be inexact as additional inspection and assessment of these materials is needed. This series is split into two sub-series, one for films that Reese worked on (titled "Produced") and one for films that he collected (titled "Collected").
  The material in this series is located in the safety vaults of the Moving Image Department at George Eastman Museum. For inquiries regarding access to these materials, please contact the Film Study Center at filmstudycenter@eastman.org
  Material is arranged following George Eastman Museum protocol for film cataloging.
  - Subseries 1, Produced, undated, 1955-1973
    - Art Patterns of the Northwest Coast Indians, 1955
      16mm print.
    - Wings Over Hanford, ca. 1956
    - Hands Across the Atom, ca. 1956
    - The Prosperity of Water, ca. 1960
    - Hands of Industry, 1962
    - Dr. Lipshitz's Fairytale, ca. 1963
    - What is a College?, ca. 1968
    - Bergen Swamp - May 1968
    - Bergen Swamp - Fall 1968
    - Bergen Swamp - Spring 1969
    - Bergen Swamp - September 1969
    - Bergen Swamp - Winter 1969
    - Dance Film - LeRoi Jones Poetry, 1969
    - Bergen Swamp - July 1970
    - Bergen Swamp - July 1970
    - Bergen Swamp Outtakes, ca. 1970
    - Botany, ca. 1970
    - The Faces of Jocotepec, 1970
      16mm print and 1/4" magnetic audio tape.
    - Brockport Resident Dance Co. in Dress Rehearsals - Spring Concerts - April 1971, ca. 1971
    - Brockport Resident Dance Co. - Dance #3 "Field of Light", ca. 1972
    - Dance #4", ca. 1972
    - The Ernst Rosenkrantz Piano, 1972
    - Cities of the Ancient Mayas - Part 1, Palenque, 300-900 A.D., 1973
    - Bonampak, ca. 1973
    - Uxmal, ca. 1973
    - Mating behavior of the European corn borer: Ostrinia nubilalis, 1973
    - An Adventure in Metallurgy: The Micro-Deformation and Fracture in Uranium, undated
    - The Color Patterns of Uranium Under Stress, undated
    - Remember the Face, undated
    - Space Science Laboratory, undated
    - The Second Look First, undated
    - Shelley: The Idealist, undated
    - [Various Rolls], undated
    - Falls, undated
    - Quest for Value, undated
    - [Various Mags Rolls], undated
    - Expedition to the Red Planet, undated
    - #5 Constellations, undated
    - Flowering Trees in the Northeast United States, undated
    - [100, 101], undated
    - [Blank], undated
    - [Blank], undated
    - [?], undated
    - [Unidentified], undated
  - Subseries 2, Collected, undated, ca. 1941-1945
    - Target for Tonight, 1941
    - Pincers of Japan, 1944
    - Weapon of War, 1944
    - China Crisis (Flying Tigers), 1945
    - Mission Completed, 1945
    - You Are There, undated
    - Berocken Point, undated
    - Great Floor, undated
    - Sky Guys, undated
    - Coming Home, undated
- Series 5, Scripts,, undated, 1954-ca. 1973
  Consists of 13 folders containing film scripts (some for unproduced works), shot lists, and accompanying illustrations.
  All folders are housed in Box C111. Original order was maintained.
  - no title (Box C111)
    - Barney – Original and Carbon, ca. 1967 (Folder 1)
      Script for Where's Barney. Two copies, with revisions.
    - Barney, ca. 1967 (Folder 2)
      Script for Where's Barney. Multiple copies, with revisions and notations.
    - Uxmal, ca. 1973 (Folder 3)
      Script for Cities of the Ancient Mayas – Part One, Palenque and Cities of the Ancient Mayas – Part 2, Uxmal, with revisions and notations.
    - Tree Flowers Script, undated (Folder 4)
      Script for Flowering Trees in the Northeast United States.
    - [What Is a College], ca. 1968 (Folder 20)
      Spiral-bound scenario for What Is a College: Brockport in Transition 100 Years. Yellow cover.
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp, July 1971 (Folder 23)
      Film script by Jean Bobear.
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp April 1970 (Folder 24)
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp September 1969 (Folder 25)
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp February 1969 (Folder 26)
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp, October 1968 (Folder 27)
    - Floristic Associations of Bergen Swamp May 1968 (Folder 28)
    - Scripts / Articles, 1954; 1956 (Folder 30)
      Black three-ring binder containing script for Art Patterns of the Northwest Coast Indians and script and story synopsis for The Theft of the Sun. The binder does not contain articles as labeled.
    - [Unlabeled Black Album], 1957 (Folder 31)
      Bound script for The Theft of the Sun, with illustration on cover, pencil drawings, and photographs.